you
and then started the applications of the
intersection theory intersection number
broadly speaking we discussed two
classes of applications number one
chapter for two maps mappings number two
chapter five two vector fields or
dynamical systems mappings and dynamical
systems I'd like to tell you that there
are many many other applications I think
at this level and in this style we could
have gone on discussing a huge variety
of applications how do you use the
machinery of intersection theory and
some other allied concepts for perhaps
another three weeks I can double the
amount but because we had the limitation
of time we stop this and I try to select
an interesting of variety but there are
many many more things you could do in
principle if you have to make some time
now before the chapter 4 we discussed
the fixed theory fixed point feelings I
say theorems in floor because there were
different versions the key to applying
topology or intersection theory to
instead of fixed points plus the think
of the mapping as a graph you take the
product of the manifold with itself and
you draw the graph of that
ruff at the same time you have to
consider the diagonal of this product
which is not and you notice that the
intersection points of the clouds and
the diaper data graph who had known
other than the fixed points is mapping
that was the interpretation and you also
remember that finally fixed points is a
very important procedure because for
example solution any equation need
algebra differential what-have-you was
reducible to finding fixed box ok so
from now on whenever you want to solve
any equation an equation there is one
way of looking at it there are many
other ways of course but an additional
way to look at it is to think in terms
of fixed points good so famous concept
here was that complex number after so
unless it by the way left edge was a
mathematician in the very active in the
first half of the twentieth century and
the little data of Russian origin
he came from Russia went to Paris and
became an engineer in Paris
unfortunately while he was a young
engineer a laboratory accident took
place
an explosion blew of both his hands
really terrible instant so he lost his
hands literally he couldn't become a be
an engineer anymore so he studied
mathematics and became one of the
leading most influential mathematicians
20th century that's it he later
emigrated to the United States and spent
most of his career at Princeton that's
just number and this was denoted by
funny symbol which that looks like
somebody walking lambda capital of F is
equal to the intersection of these
diagonal will be graph of and if this
number is non zero that means that well
in particular they must be intersection
points into computing plus or minus one
so there must be fixed points that was a
logic here which is called left it's
fixed point theorem is almost there for
a tautology Toto she means that same
exactly what the definition saying that
if the lessons lambda of a mark on 0
implies the map must have six points as
it stands this theorem will not be very
useful because you know by now I hope
you're sufficiently prepared the
pictorial thinking that it's saying the
same thing but the power of this map
however this not comes from the previous
theorem 17 in this chapter that when you
calculate verses number you see it's the
intersection number in fact and the
intersection number is invariant under
isotopy so if you want to find me that's
just number or if you want to find a
fixed point of some map as far as the
number of fixed points is concerned you
don't have to use the original map you
can deformed or zoom up to something
simpler and count delicious number for
something much simpler and then you know
that that number is the number it's not
the photo original map a very beautiful
forming a problem to something simpler
and solving the problem in the simpler
version okay and as a consequence we can
find fixed points in case you want to
calculate this number for a map that is
given in terms of formulas often in
applied contexts applied situations you
have to calculate the largest number but
from formula definitions now there was a
phone rang and it was that you take the
sum over all the fixed points for X you
calculate the derivative of Y or not in
general it is the acromion X is M by M
matrix subtract the identity map it
looks a bit like the characters the
polynomial and there is a relationship
and then you take the determinant and
look at the sign and that sign plus or
minus corresponds exactly to plus minus
signs of the intersections this formula
although it looks very impressive is
quite difficult use but we have used it
in some simple situations and then as a
direct correlations we had the browser
fix points perhaps this is historically
the most famous of the fixed point
theorems and it is one that was used
most often outside
but you should realize that this is a
direct consequence of left chefs
having said it's a direct consequence
braava says that if you have a
continuous map from a bowl to itself it
has a fixed point no further such
containers map any continuous map from
the port itself fixed on a bowl has
abounded left set supplies of course the
manifolds without the boundary so we
have to have a little trick to reduce
our deduce relevant lessons and that
trick experiment we do some pictures
there consists of projection stirring
and embedding nonetheless before all
that braava is the direct consequence of
the access and we have many many
applications after applications due to
the el badi theorem so if you like this
is a status for equilibrium in a Markov
chain application ability or status code
in physics and we also mentioned we did
not quite explain but Nash equilibrium
in games the comics
and he also remember the rather
facetious discussion about stirring
coffee or dropping a map and so on
publications are nearly endless okay
and then the final chapter was an
application this time moving from maps
to data fields for Terran persistence
equilibria or things in a way fixed
functions a concern with maps in other
words so global behavior a topological
behavior of some movement whereas vector
fields are local movements so this is
global application of local application
of intersection theory if you like as
someone's intriguing and tricky concept
suddenly tricky to visualize the concept
of tangent that was a little difficult
you have to think of the tangent spaces
as vertical that was the only way to
draw the picture but we did anyway and
here the way to think about the
application is as follows the tangent
bundle was drawn like this and the base
manifold Emma strong like this and there
is a zero section which is identified
with
bass and what is the vector field well
vector field looks like this and that's
the gamma D drug for the vector field
lady to the zero section and the gamma
of the intersect none other than its
zero so the vector field that is
equilibrium
you might remember these two pictures
like this you see in the fixed-point
case you are intersecting the graph by
something that's tilted 45 degrees here
in the case of a Philippa of the profuse
you are intersecting graph will
something that's flat zero degree but
that's the only difference you just
leave the practice or projective
practice and the idea is the same it's
always thinking in terms of the
intersections thinking in terms of
simplifying the picture by deformation
so in this case we had the concept of
index over vector field he was simply
plus or minus of the intersection of
science and index of a vector field
could be calculated in principle and if
we had to calculate it in terms of a
formula that was a formula it's a
summation over all equilibria of V given
up the field and if you sum the index of
V and X what did you get well we got
precisely the picture makes it
abundantly clear the intersection of the
zero section and the graph of the vector
field or the section of the let the
field as we say professional terms and
then sometimes just as indicated
reference number you might have to
calculate the index from a formula
sometimes the vector field of dynamical
system is already given by a formula in
applied context practical stations well
you should know that in principle if you
had a large sheet of paper and a clear
mind and a cup of coffee you can
calculate everything and the calculation
formula is that index of the Bacchus
remember this is a vector field and this
is a point is simply equal to well first
you calculate the derivative of V as
before it is really the acromion the M
by n matrix of partial derivatives and
then you think that you are going to
subtract the identity but you don't hear
identity because I was comparing the
graph here we are comparing the graph
with zero Degree at 0 degree sink so you
subtract nothing you subtract zero you
look at the determinant of this and then
you look at the sign and that is the
index of V X and then in order to have a
very beautiful series of nonlinear
applications we introduce the concept
first met in our exercise session of
Euler characteristic which we denoted by
P this was simply the following you just
do a suitable reasonable network on your
mind for here divides patties shown your
manifold into the network you can think
of the example the 2d you have a surface
vertices edges faces and you draw a
network if you like a map of countries
and the other characters was B to 0
minus beta 1 plus beta 2 minus beta 3
plus minus plus minus plus in front of
all the even dimensions minus in front
of all dimensions is alternating some
alternating sum of numbers of cells in
all dimensions and that turns out
this is a combinatorial definition
combinatory mean that you draw a graph
sell your contracts and then you count
but it is it turns out it's not clear
from the definition but it turns out to
the topological concept it does not
depend on how you partitioned what kind
of what kind of network you took and
then I'm sorry I'm going to overflow the
main theorem of this chapter was the
beautiful and powerful theorem due to
Fontana and course
hop theorem which is parallel to the
lessons 6-ton 6.0 it says but it has a
slightly different flavor that if you
take the sum of all the indices well we
already know what that is it is the
intersection number between the zero
section and the graph of you that's the
field but you can say even more it turns
out to be the Euler characteristic of
the manifold you recall that this can be
used to this great film can be used in
two different directions way it's a
single theory so how we use it is up to
us up to our psychology up to practical
needs you can imagine that you know
something about the left hand side let's
say that you have a picture of a vector
field or dynamical system of water flow
you remember that example so that you
can calculate all the indices that
knowledge of dynamical systems tells you
something about the Euler characteristic
of a manifold analogous dynamical system
gives you information about topology or
you can go in the other direction if you
happen to know the Euler characteristic
of the manifold and that's very easy
remember you just partition computer if
you know something about the Euler
characteristic well that means that the
sum of indices cannot be arbitrary it
puts a constraint on the kind of
dynamical systems you can have yes so
topology gave you information about
burning persistence this kind of
collection between two so-called
different areas of mathematics is very
difficult it's so typical in fact that
you should be aware of the following
fact you know when you go around the
world and people colleagues and others
meet you
they often ask what's your field my
several I do mathematics of salt and
then they ask o arian mathematics but
that question is a little strange if you
think about it it's like saying what do
you eat
I say well I put some things so you
specialize in me yes
you never eat vegetables or fish fluid
and I said I also eat fish and rice and
vegetables that fruits and so and they
say oh you're such a multidisciplinary
person well I mean mathematics science
in broad terms and nature itself doesn't
know that we are making all those
strange distinctions and partitioning
the science into little compartments
which are called forces ok at schools
and universities for convenience
maybe we choose to devote a whole
semester differential equations we may
choose to devote whole semester to
algebra all to discussion topology and
so on but that does not mean that's just
a convenience that doesn't mean that the
science is divided and those connections
are all over the place
so please explore those connections and
indeed is by exploring those connections
that you can solve interesting problems
new problems if you are stuck in a field
you are likely to make some
contributions but those contributions
will be textbook contributions yeah
because the tools were prepared for
exactly those problems so nobody will be
surprised if you solve problems using
the tools that were designed for those
problems but using connections like this
you can apply tools from one field to
another field so you can find surprising
results which is what we want to look
for in life then the simplest corollary
of this was the fact that the number of
equilibria of a vector field report an
open system that you can draw on the
mind fault please remember this is the
general situation not the general if
it's degenerate you have to shake the
picture of any manner
of any vector field on the month of the
end is bounded below the useful bound by
the Euler characteristic but even the
absolute value of the helicopters in
particular if the older characteristic
is nonzero you cannot have a vector
field with without singularity or in
other words if the Euler characteristic
is zero every vector field every
dynamical system on the manifold must
have equilibria master points where the
vector field vanishes must have
singularities as some people say so
applications again in the similar vein
to applications that we had for that
sense we have impossibility of forming a
hedgehog
existence of singularities or matrix in
general activity and so on and as a
dessert as an appendix we discussed just
one more result which can be approached
by the topological pictorial idea which
is the fundamental fundamental theorem
of algebra
you realize that although that's the
traditional name every impose it
fundamental theorem of algebra it's
actually not quite a theorem of algebra
it's real nature is to possible it has
to do with rhyming numbers he has to do
with degree you or some intersectional
theory background but anyway it says
that every complex polynomial has at
least one root and from that you can use
that has in fact as many as the degree
of polynomial and that can be deduced by
a very nice tuples for is the whole
picture clear what we have done then is
to look at many many pictures of many
examples that's how we started and then
we'll introduce the concept of
deformation it's called as to be
information of those pictures
information stationed deformation of you
problems default to something simple so
the simpler problem I come back and the
intersection number was in the
environment that we looked at number is
fortunately in the invariant under
deformation and then we discussed two
classes of applications fixed points and
equilibrium of vector fields in the
fixed point theorem the main result was
left sets fixed point theorem and in the
equilibria actually in the equilibrium
vector fields may resolve this formula
hope that's the summary of the entire
course as given at Ames
one anecdote about one edition about
left shirts I told you who - it was this
courageous man and very interesting
personality
the google him read about him on
Wikipedia or something like that you are
related to their ships the reason is
that sheds
migrated to America and became a
professor at Princeton and he trained
quite a lot of good mathematicians at
Princeton and one of the his students
were called steam rod and Steven became
a leading dermatologist of the age he
died relatively young and still not had
many students and one of them was called
John Moore and again Moore was great
specialist in homotopy theory and very
imaginative mathematician again peculiar
character but a great mathematician and
Moore had a student William Browder
brother was really the greatest figure
in the field of Golden Age apology
geometry in the 1960s and 70s starting a
little bit early about 60s and 70s and
he constructed the theory of surgery we
discussed surgery but there was four
dimension to it turns out you can do the
same thing in all dimensions and you
might remember mentioning the Khan
Khattak conjecture remember super
conjecture very famous event that was
solved was concerned with three
dimensional manifolds but in that
connection you might remember my
mentioning that well
classification of man Falls is a very
difficult problem it turns out however
that in dimension 5 and above up to
something called formato P you can
classify man falls which is quite
surprising and amazing theory huge body
work and grab a brother not proud why by
the way brother
was responsible it was one of the chief
athletes together with Navi co-founder
Simon and others Sullivan was the
student Brown Brothers of that
development surgery Theory all
dimensions and you have connected flesh
yet because when I did my PhD at
Princeton I was officially a student of
brothers and I now came to share picture
own wisdom with you let's take a break
welcome and at 9:30
please come back you can come back ready
to alia if you like but 9:30 shop
probably 10 minutes will be enough for
people to have a veto tournament in
question and please allow us one or two
minutes and because that's an
interesting question I'd like to address
in public in front of you
secrets question is left sex lost both
his hands as a young man terrible
terrible situation is it possible to do
mathematics without hands well clearly
yes because he left a very important
legacy mathematics very influential
mathematician wonderful results are
wonderful perspective but there have
been examples like this in mathematics
you see there people who didn't have
hands within mathematics and at the
highest level very creative another
example from the area of topology and
geometry is that upon triage pontryagin
russian mathematician was totally blind
from not from birth but from very early
childhood from a kh7 or a totally blind
but he turn became one of the great
Jonathas of the year how can you do
geometry when you don't see well he was
seeing an awful lot lots and lots of
things that we most of the rest of us
cannot see but he was seeing them in his
head so he could follow very very
intricate and very delicate and
beautiful constructions and operations
in higher dimensions song in his if nine
totally blank and yet mathematician the
first track there have been other
examples of blind mathematicians for
example a person that I know personally
is somebody called Immanuel view at Lyon
in France
he's a very tall mathematician I'm
totally blind as well but he's one of
the leading geometers of our time so you
can see things you can see things you
can do things and you can overcome
difficulties and I happen to know that
there people also who go on to become
really creative and leading scientists
of the era coming back coming from say
war zones there's an example in Vietnam
there are people who come from really
poor backgrounds really impoverished
minimal conditions and they yet we have
to have a lot of luck but nonetheless
they make it in science and they
contribute to the advancement of
knowledge and they're people who come
from all kinds of backgrounds and all
kinds of cultures all kinds of
conditions but with hard work with help
from others and helping one another and
with a little bit of luck you can also
make